A Guide to the John Steinbeck Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6239-j
John Steinbeck Collection 1934-1962
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6239-j
ca. 41 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase-Deposit [ 1971 Dec 27 ] 1972 Mar 13
Item Listing
- Letters
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1935 Aug 22]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses
    Jedworth
    [
    Jedwick
    ], publishers, publishing slowly, a planned trip to Mexico and lack of gift for money-making.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1935 Sep]; ALS, 2 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses dislike for Hollywood, preparation for a trip to Mexico, prerequisites for fame; briefly discusses
    , [Pascal] Covici's reissuing two early books [
    The Pastures of Heaven
    and
    To a God Unknown
    ] and availability of a copy of [
    Tortilla Flat
    ]; mentions Carmel, Woodstock, Left Bank, Laguane Beach and [ San Francisco].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [late 1935]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses Paramount [Pictures] purchase of a book [
    ], his next book [
    In Dubious Battle
    ], their stay in Mexico, his dislike of New York City, Ben Abramson, Frances [? Toor], American tourists in Mexico and Mexican Indians; mentions Pacific Grove, California. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Feb]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses dislike of Communists and difficulty publishing short stories; briefly discusses dislike of [David Herbert] Lawrence, not caring what the press will do,
    Esquire
    , [Arnold] Gingrich, McIntosh and Otis [Literary Agency], [Arthur Burton] Rascoe, ignorance of the theater,
    The North American Review
    and fear of getting down to work; mentions
    New Testament
    , New York City and
    Journey's End
    . ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Feb]; ALS, 2 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses a bad review [of
    ] by Mary Ann McCarthy[ Mary Theresa McCarthy] in
    The Nation
    briefly discusses Paul's rejected book, [Arnold] Gingrich's request for stories for
    , his new book [
    Of Mice and Men
    ], a possible visit by Paul, Herman Shumlin's production of the play
    and his problems getting published; mentions
    Caesar's Commentaries
    , Plato,
    , Joseph Henry Jackson, [
    San Francisco] Chronicle
    , Covici [Friede], Ben Abramson, his agents [ McIntosh and Otis Literary Agency] and Hollywood. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Apr 6]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses his current work [
    ], [William] Heineman's publishing [
    ], death of his British agent, Paul's coming west and weather; mentions [William] Saroyan. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Jun 11]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a new house in Los Gatos, Paul's novel, difficulty with his new manuscript [
    ] and the Republican Convention.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Jun 22]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses rain water as a symbol of security; briefly discusses his wife's [ Carol Henning Steinbeck] building a new house [in Los Gatos], Paul's visit, [ John Ernst Steinbeck] and "the new thing" [
    ]; mentions [ Pacific Grove].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Aug 25]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses an article for
    , a series ["
    The Harvest Gypsies
    "] for the [
    San Francisco] News
    ], Paul's
    A Horse in Arizona
    , discovering a book "down the country" [
    The Grapes of Wrath
    ] and a story he wrote for
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1936 Dec]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses Los Gatos, a very long book [
    ], [Paul's
    ], his new book [
    ] and a planned trip east; mentions his wife [ Carol Henning Steinbeck].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Jan 6]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses happiness in his work on the book [
    ], a possible trip to New York, possible sources of a copy of "the little book" [?
    Saint Katy the Virgin
    ], repair of a rain-damaged pool, a bad cold, drinking too much and the need to conserve money; mentions his sisters [ Elizabeth Steinbeck Ainsworth, Esther Steinbeck Rodgers, Mary Steinbeck Dekker], [Arthur Burton] Rascoe, Harry Hansen and [Pascal] Covici. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Jan 27]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses unhappiness with his work [
    ], a possible trip, his last book [
    ], the weather in California, the sausage works [ Multch Sausage Manufacturing Co.] and the death of [Arthur Burton] Rascoe's son [ Albert Burton Rascoe]; mentions
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Mar 7]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a review in [
    New York Herald Tribune
    ], a trip to New York City and the sausage works [ Multch Sausage Manufacturing Co.].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 May 4]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a visit to New York City; mentions Bedford Hotel. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Aug 15]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses being in the Atlantic Ocean near Greenland, plans upon landing in Albany, expecting Paul on the West Coast and a visit to New York City. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Aug]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses a job [the script for the play
    ], a trip to Europe and a desire to see Paul.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Nov 12]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a visit from Paul, his return from a trip, the house being a mess, Paul's hat, Carol Henning Steinbeck's need for a break, a planned Thanksgiving with the Jackson family[ Joseph Henry Jackson and Charlotte E. Cobden Jackson] and being too busy too spend an afternoon with Paul and [ Joseph Henry Jackson]; mentions Monterey and Mary [P. Engargiola Paul].]
  - [ John Steinbeck] to Mary [P. Engargiola Paul] and Louis Paul, [1937 Fall]; TL, 1 p.
    [Discusses a house warming party, Paul's hat, getting a phone and Paul's former job; mentions [Joseph Henry] Jackson, Charlotte [E. Cobden] Jackson, Ritchie Lovejoy and his wife [ Natalya Lovejoy], the Bengston family, Long Island, Burlingame, Multch Sausage Manufacturing Co. and Elsa Maxwell. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1937 Dec 28]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a story by Paul ["
    A Lucky Day for Private Smoot
    "] in the January issue of
    mentions Mary [P. Engargiola Paul]. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], [late 1937 or early 1938]Monday; TL, 1 p.
    [Discusses a proposed trip with [ Joseph Henry Jackson], a brief visit to the Jackson family and his rewriting [?
    ].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], [late 1937]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses his and Carol Henning Steinbeck's praise for a manuscript by Paul; mentions Hollywood, Blingham [ Burlingame].]
  - [ John Steinbeck] to Louis Paul, [1938 Jan 1]; TPC
    [Discusses stopping by Paul's, a trip by Carol Henning Steinbeck and a manuscript by Ritch[ie Lovejoy].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul and Mary [P. Engargiola] Paul, [1938 Mar 22]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a razor, a lily and having a good time.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1938 Aug 3]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses things interfering with his work [
    ], Carol Henning Steinbeck's sore throat, "the eastern matter," a visit from Brod[erick] Crawford and the ranch; mentions [Charles] Scribner's [Sons]. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul and Mary [P. Engargiola] Paul, [1938 Sep 6]; APCS(w/transcript)
    (title source, method of work and typing by Carol Henning Steinbeck); mentions "
    Battle Hymn of the Republic
    . "]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1938 Oct 18]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses not wanting to hear criticism until he is finished [with
    ]; briefly discusses weariness.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1939 Jul 6] Thursday; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses a bad leg, his tonsillectomy and his unlisted phone number; mentions Mary [P. Engargiola Paul]; includes pencilled poem in another hand.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1939 Jul 15]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses his illness and not stopping by Paul's trip to Santa Cruz. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1940 May]; TL, 1 p. (w/xerox)
    [Discusses a planned trip [to Mexico to film
    The Forgotten Village
    ], the ranch, Mary [P. Engargiola Paul's ] illness, Paul's garden and a trip to the Gulf [of California] to collect animals.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1940 Dec]; TL, 1 p. (w/xerox)
    [Discusses sending both books to Carnahans; briefly discusses working on the "marine book" [
    Sea of Cortez
    ], returning from filming [
    ] in Mexico, plans to work with [Lewis] Milestone[on the film
    The Red Pony
    ] and a dog for Paul; mentions Monterey. ]
  - John Steinbeck to [ Louis Paul], [1941 Mar]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses an invitation to Paul to visit, the return of Carol Henning Steinbeck and work on the book [
    Sea Of Cortez
    ], mentions Joe [Higashi].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], [1941 May]; TLS, 1 p. (w/xerox)
    [Discusses [ Pascal Covici's ] sale of the little Mexican book of pictures [
    ]; briefly discusses a book Paul sent, a house in Pacific Grove, sale of the ranch, working hard on the gulf book [
    ], himself as "half bum and half voluptuary and half workman" and his bad nerves; mentions Ed[ward Flanders Ricketts], his agents [ McIntosh and Otis Literary Agency], Mary [P. Engargiola Paul] and a film [
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [1941 Jul 15]; APCS(w/transcript)
    [Discusses "that silly thing" getting to [Herb] Caen, his knife, Paul's hospitality and a new pen.]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], [1941 Jul]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses "future leaks" especially to [Leonard] Lyons, his knife, work on the second draft [of
    ], a possible trip to Los Angeles, [ MacIntosh and Otis Literary Agency] and [ Pascal Covici] liking the book, and plans to work on ["
    God in the Pipes
    "]; mentions Mary [P. Engargiola Paul] and Gwyndolyn Conger. ]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], [1943 Dec]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses Paul's book and [World War II].]
  - John Steinbeck to Louis Paul, [ca. 1946 May]; ALS, 1 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses moving to an old house, a proposed visit from Paul, Gwyndolyn Conger Steinbeck's pregnancy, another book [
    The Wayward Bus
    ] and a trip to Mexico. ]
  - Louis Paul to John Steinbeck, [1962] Oct 29; TLS, 1 p. (carbon)
    [Discusses the return of some letters to Steinbeck and Steinbeck's Nobel Prize in Literature; mentions
    New York Times Book Review
  - John Steinbeck to Louis [Paul], 1962 Nov; ALS, 2 p. (w/transcript)
    [Discusses his reasons for returning to Paul the letters Paul had returned to him, his fear of prizes, [Nobel Prize in Literature], the Soviet Union rewriting its history, Paul's inking out hurtful references to living persons (except Mary McCarthy) in the letters and Walt Whitman. ]
- Photograph
  - John Steinbeck, seated, [early 1930's]; Photo
    [" Sonya Noskowiak" written below lower right corner; photo appeared in the
    , 1937 Feb 28.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Map made by John Steinbeck for Louis Paul, giving directions to [first] house in Los Gatos, with four negatives, [mid to late 1936]; Map
  - Notes made by [ Mary P. Engargiola Paul] regarding John Steinbeck's personal life and a chronology of his works, [1962 or later]; Notes, 6 p. (xerox)
    [Discusses the rift between John Steinbeck and Carol Henning Steinbeck, Steinbeck's relationship with [ Gwyndolyn Conger] and other women, including [Natalya] Lovejoy, his reluctance to leave either Pacific Grove or the first house in Los Gatos, his health and poor diet, his sexual problems, Carol's discomfort with wealth and his becoming too "rich" non-monetarily; mentions
    ,
    , Ritchie Lovejoy,
    and Louis [Paul]. ]